let's discuss the relationship between
lsq entries Robin trees and reservation
stations when we issue a load or a store
instruction we need a robe and three
every instruction needs a Robin tree so
when we issue a non load store
instruction we also get a robe and tree
and we get for a non load store
instruction a reservation station of the
right type for loads and stores instead
we get a lsq entry this act as
reservation stations for loads and
stores so note that we cannot issue a
load or a store unless we have both a
Rob entry available and then lsq entry
available just like we couldn't issue a
non load store instruction if we didn't
have both a Rob enter available and the
reservation station of the right type
available when we execute a load store
instruction there are actually two parts
to that execution first we need to
compute the address second we need to
produce the value for a load that means
we first compute the address then we get
the value from memory for a store
actually this can happen in any order we
are computing the address while we are
also trying to obtain the value of the
register that we need to store to memory
we write the result only for loads for a
store there is no right of the result
the store simply keeps the value and the
address in the lost or queue for other
loads to get it and for the store to
finally send it to memory on commit but
the load as soon as it gets the result
will broadcast that result to dependent
instructions so that pretty much all the
reservation stations that are waiting
for that register value can now proceed
so note that our load store unit
although it doesn't have reservation
stations it has the load/store queue so
when it finally figures out the value
for the load it needs to broadcast it to
subsequent instructions so that they can
be woken up and use that value they will
get that value from the load/store queue
to commit a load we move the arrow big
head basically we freed our Arobin tree
and we also move the lsq head that is we
freed the lsq entry and we need to do
the same thing for stores for stores in
addition to this we have to send the
right to memory pretty much we've been
holding on to the address in the value
until we commit the store so at the time
when we commit it we need to finally
send that
to memory